A Finding Aid to the Emily Genauer papers, circa 1920s-1990s, in the Archives of American Art AAA.genaemil
Archives of American Art
Emily Genauer papers
circa 1920-1990
AAA.genaemil
Archives of American Art
10.1 Linear feet
The papers of art critic Emily Genauer measure 10.1 linear feet and date from circa 1920 to 1990. Found within the papers are correspondence with artists, gallery owners, and friends; extensive writings; research and reference files; personal business records; and photographs. Notable correspondents include David Aronson, Mrs. Max Beckman, Isabel Bishop, Dorothy Carnegie, Marc Chagall, Salvatore Dali, Stuart Davis, Martha Graham, Harry F. Guggenheim, Irene Rice Pereira, Clyfford Still, Rufino Tamayo, and Frank Lloyd Wright, among many others.
Genauer, Emily, 1910-
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 6 series.
Series 1: Correspondence and Letters, 1938-1991 (Box 1, 12, 0.8 linear feet)
Series 2: Writings, circa 1930s-1990s (Box 1-3, 2.5 linear feet)
Series 3: Research and Reference Files, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4-6, 2.6 linear feet)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1933-1992 (Box 6-7, 0.8 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Materials, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 7-9, 12, 1.6 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1930s-1970s (Box 9-11, 12, 1.8 linear feet)
Separated Materials note
Also found in the Archives are 300 letters lent for microfilming on reels NG1 that were not included in later donations. Loaned material is available in Archives' offices and for interlibrary loan but it is not described in the container list of this finding aid.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of art critic Emily Genauer measure 10.1 linear feet and date from circa 1920 to 1990. Found within the papers are correspondence with artists, gallery owners, and friends; extensive writings; research and reference files; personal business records; and photographs.
Notable correspondents include David Aronson, Mrs. Max Beckman, Isabel Bishop, Dorothy Carnegie, Marc Chagall, Salvatore Dali, Stuart Davis, Martha Graham, Harry F. Guggenheim, Irene Rice Pereira, Clyfford Still, Rufino Tamayo, and Frank Lloyd Wright, among numerous others. Extensive writings consist largely of drafts of columns written by Genauer and supporting research notes, as well as essays, speeches, lectures, book manuscripts, and memoirs. Research and reference files include source material for columns and essays. Personal business records document Genauer's work on committees and arts organizations, juries, awards, honors and also include interview transcripts and other personal scattered files. There is material regarding her leaving the New York World-Telegram. Printed material includes two of Genauer's books, magazines, newspaper clippings, and exhibition catalogs. Photographs are portraits of Genauer and of artwork.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Emily Genauer papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in 2000 and 2003 by her daughter, Constance Roche.
Biographical/Historical note
Emily Genauer (1911-2002) was a modern art critic and columinst working in New York City from 1932 until well into the 1980s. In 1974, she won the Pulitzer Prize for distinguished art criticism.
Genauer was born in 1911 in Staten Island. She attended Hunter College and Columbia University, majoring in Journalism. She began her writing career in 1929 with the New York World, which later became the New York World-Telegram. She became a strong advocate for modern art and sculpture and introduced modern artists like Marc Chagall and Diego Rivera to the newspaper audience. She also followed lesser known artists and often visited their studios, and they, in return, regularly read her articles and reviews of their shows.
Genauer left the New York World-Telegram in 1949 after a dispute with the owner who accused her writing as overly sympathetic to "Communists and left-wingers" and told her she could no longer write about Picasso. She immediately went to work as the art critic for the New York Herald Tribune, where she worked until 1967, when it folded. She then wrote a regular column for the Newsday Syndicate until the mid-1970s. She also worked for Harper's and in television and served on the council for the National Endowment for the Humanities from 1966 to 1970. Genauer was the author of a number of books, including The Best of Art, Chagall at the Met, and Rufino Tamayo.
Genauer passed away in 2002 in New York City at the age of 91.
Aronson, David; Bishop, Isabel, 1902-1988; Carnegie, Dorothy; Chagall, Marc, 1887-; Dalí, Salvador, 1904-; Davis, Stuart, 1892-1964; Graham, Martha; Guggenheim, Harry Frank, 1890-; Pereira, I. Rice (Irene Rice), 1902-1971; Still, Clyfford, 1904-; Tamayo, Rufino, 1899-; Wright, Frank Lloyd, 1867-1959; Art critics--New York (State)--New York; Essays; Gallery owners--New York (State)--New York; Interviews; Lectures; Photographs; Speeches; Transcriptions; Women art critics--New York (State)--New York
- Correspondence and Letters, 1938-1991; Series 1; 0.8 Linear feet Box 1, 12
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence dates from 1938 to 1991 and documents Emily Genauer's relationships with artists, gallery owners, and other colleagues. Notable correspondents include Robert Anderson, Alfred H. Barr, Jr., S.N. Behrman, Dorothy Carnegie, Marc Chagall, Stuart Davis, Philip Evergood, Herbert Ferber, Martha Graham, Balcomb Greene, George Grosz, Harry F. Guggenheim, Philip Guston, Doris Humphrey, Robert Indiana, Yasuo Kuniyoshi, David Laventhol, Jack Levine, Jose Limon, Richard Lippold, Bill Moyers, Alice Neel, Clifford Odets, Irene Rice Pereira, Richard Pleasant, H.V. Rebay, Manuel Rivera, Harold Rome, Reuven Rubin, Antonio Salemme, David Smith, Oliver Smith, Stephen Sondheim, Clyfford Still, May Stevens, Rufino Tamayo, Virgil Thomson, Jack Tworkov, Max Weber, Frank Lloyd Wright, Ossip Zadkin, and William Zorach. Also included is a pair of rubber underpants that were sent to Emily Genauer by artist Clyfford Still, after she had reviewed his work unfavorably in the New York Herald Tribune. The attached note reads: "Hoping this will aid in concealing your Sunday afflictions. With the compliments of Clyfford Still."
  - A, 1947-1972; 1 Folders (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - B, 1947-1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chagall, Marc, 1955-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - C, 1944-1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - D, 1946-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - E, 1951-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - F, 1945-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - G, 1944-1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - H, 1947-1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - I-K, 1945-1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - L, 1944-1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - M, 1944-1990 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - N, 1944-1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - O, 1944-1955 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Pereira, Irene Rice, 1947-1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - P, 1943-1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - R, 1945-1975 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Still, Clyfford, Rubber Underpants with Note, circa 1949-1966 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - S, 1938-1984 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - T-V, 1939-1971 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - W-Z, 1947-1976 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1935-1974 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letter Fragments, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Writings, circa 1930s-1990s; Series 2; 2.5 Linear feet Box 1-3
  Extensive writings date from circa 1930 to 1990 and consist largely of drafts of columns Genauer wrote for the New York World, New York World-Telegram, New York Herald Tribune and the New York World Journal Tribune, as well as research materials. Also included are drafts and notes for books, including Best of Art, drafts of essays, and lecture notes. Clippings of Emily Genauer's columns are also be found in research and reference files and printed materials.
  - Book Drafts and Notes, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Book Introduction, Notes, and Research Materials, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Draft of Best of Art and Research Material, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Drafts of Essays and Research Materials, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Drafts of Essays and Research Materials, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Drafts of Essays and Research Materials, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Drafts of Essays, Newspaper Columns, and Research Materials, circa 1930s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Drafts of Essays, Newspaper Columns, and Research Materials, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Drafts of Essays, Newspaper Columns, and Research Materials, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Drafts of Newspaper Columns and Research Material, circa 1930-1970s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Drafts of Newspaper Columns and Research Material, circa 1930s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - Drafts of Newspaper Columns and Research Material, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Drafts of Newspaper Columns and Research Material, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Drafts of Newspaper Columns and Research Material, circa 1940s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Drafts of Newspaper Columns and Research Material, circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 9-11)
  - Drafts of Newspaper Columns and Research Material, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 12-14)
  - Drafts of Newspaper Columns and Research Material, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - Drafts of Newspaper Columns and Research Material, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Drafts of Newspaper Columns and Research Material, circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 18-23)
  - Drafts of Newspaper Columns and Research Material, circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
  - Drafts of Newspaper Columns and Research Material, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 6-8)
  - Drafts of Newspaper Columns and Research Material, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
  - Drafts of Newspaper Columns and Research Material, circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Drafts, Notes, and Research Material, circa 1930s-1950s (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Drafts of Publishing Correspondence, circa 1940s-1990 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Draft, "The Fur-Lined Musuem", 1944 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Lecture Notes, circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
  - Lecture Notes, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
  - Lecture Notes and Research Material on Changing Art, circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Magazine Articles by Emily Genauer, 1937-1951 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Notes and Reseach Material, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Possible Book Chapter, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Research and Reference Files, circa 1920s-1990s; Series 3; 2.6 Linear feet Box 4-6
  Research and reference files date from circa 1920 to 1990 and include subject based source materials, including newspaper clippings, magazine articles, notes, press releases, and letters. Subjects include art and religion, politics, museums, such at the MET and the Whitney, and individual artists, including Salvador Dali, Marc Chagall, Henri Matisse, and Vincent Van Gogh.
  Arrangement note
  Research and reference files are arranged alphabetically by subject and labeled, where possible, with their original folder titles. Because the collection was minimally processed, contents of the folders were not checked against the original folder titles for accuracy, and all folders have the same date range.
  - Abandoned Past Projects, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Art Collecting, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Art Council, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Art and Industry, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - Art Market Scams, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Art Market, Van Gogh, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Art and Politics, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Art and Religion, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Art and the Social Scene, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Francis Bacon, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Chagall and Toulouse-Lautrec, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Changing Tastes, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Congdon, Art and Religion, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Controversies, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Corporate, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Criticism, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Dali, Surrealism, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Dali and Apollo Flight, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Dada, Surrealism, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Dahli, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Willem de Kooning, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Dondero, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Free Culture, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Fuller, B., circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Giacometti, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Arshile Gorky, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Guggenheim, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - International Art, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - ISMS General, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Italian Art, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Judging Art, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Kline, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - John Marin, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Henri Matisse, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Matisse/Picasso, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Matta, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - MET, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - MET Conference, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Henry Moore, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Museums, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Nevelson, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - New York City Hospitals Project, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 15-16)
  - Georgia O'Keefe, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Opening of National Gallery, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Picasso--Guernica, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Points and Observations, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Jackson Pollack, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Re: Gash, Apartment Designed by Deskey, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Reich, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Religious Art, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Religious and Modern Art, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Russia, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Sculpture, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Sloan--Early Realism, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - David Smith, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Frank Stella, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Edward John Stevens, Jr., circa 1920s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Rufino Tamayo, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Ten Automobiles, Museum of Modern Art, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Theft and Forgery, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Van Gogh, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Van Gogh Story (Not for Book), circa 1920s-1990s (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
  - Whitney, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - WPA, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Frank Lloyd Wright, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
  - Untitled Research Files, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 6, Folder 11-16)
- Personal Business Records, 1933-1992; Series 4; 0.8 Linear feet Box 6-7
  Personal business records date from 1933-1992 and document Genauer's involvement with the National Endowment for the Humanities and other professional organizations, and art juries. Also included are business correspondence, meeting agendas, interview transcripts, edited manuscripts and research materials, and files on Communism and censorship that date around the time that Genauer left the New York Herald Tribune after being accused of promoting "Communist and left-wing" artists.
  The series also includes files called "Memories and Stories" which consist of drafts of columns, newspaper and magazine clippings, memorabilia, and notes, which were kept here according to the original order.
  - Art Advisory Board of hte Fine Arts Committee, New York City Health and Hospital Corporation, 1971-1973 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Artists for Victory, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Business Agreements, 1962-1968 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Business Correspondence, 1937-1973 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Business Correspondence, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Clippings Regarding Awards and Honors, circa 1940s-1970s (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Date Book, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Desk Calendar, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Fellowship Application, National Endowment for the Humanities, 1960s-1980s (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Interview Transcript, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Interview Transcripts, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Materials Regarding Awards and Honors, 1950s-1980s (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Materials Regarding Communism and Censorship, circa 1948-1949 (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
  - Materials Regarding Donation to Syracuse University, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Meeting Agendas, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Memo, Use of Letters, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Memories and Stories, 1930s-1980s (Box 7, Folder 7-8)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1966-1968 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, Grant Applications and Reference Material, circa 1960s (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, "Hidden Treasures: American Museums", 1971-1972 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - "New York World Telegram", Lists of Articles, 1933-1935 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Pay Statements, 1963-1966 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Pepsi-Cola "Portrait of America" Exhibit, 1944-1948 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - "Problems of the Younger American Artist," Edited Manuscript and Research Material, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Resume, circa 1980s (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Reviews, "Best of Art", 1948 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Script, "Studio Stories", circa 1950s (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Seating Chart, Town Hall Luncheon to Dr. Edith and Sir Osbert Sitwell, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Speaking Programs, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Tamayo Sale, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - "World Journal Tribune," Final Issue, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 22)
- Printed Materials, circa 1920s-1990s; Series 5; 1.6 Linear feet Box 7-9, 12
  Printed materials date from circa 1920s to 1990s. They include two of Genauer's books: Chagall at the Met and Best of Art, as well newspaper and magazine clippings by Genauer and other authors. Also included are exhibition catalogs, magazines, and an unidentified poster. Additional clippings of Emily Genauer's columns are also scattered among the research and reference files and writings.
  - Art Prints, undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Book, "American Folk Art from the Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Folk Art Collection", 1959 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Book, "Best of Art", 1948 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Book, "Chagall at the Met", 1971 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Book, "Matisse," Raymond Escholier, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Book, "Musee National Message Biblique, Marc Chagall", 1973 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Book, "The Sculpture of Max Kalish", 1933 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Book, "What's New, 1956" (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Clippings of Emily Genauer Columns, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Clippings of Emily Genauer Columns, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Clippings of Emily Genauer Columns, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
  - Clippings of Emily Genauer Columns, circa 1940s-1980 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Clippings of Emily Genauer Columns, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
  - Clippings of Emily Genauer Columns, circa 1960s (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Clippings of Emily Genauer Columns, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 9-11)
  - Clippings of Emily Genauer Columns, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 12-13)
  - Clippings of Emily Genauer Columns, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 8, Folder 14-15)
  - Ernest Hemingway, "The Old Man and the Sea", 1952 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1930s-1940s (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1947-1949 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1956-1985 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1950s (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1950s (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1963-1970 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1994-1995 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Jacques Lipchitz, circa 1960s (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Magazines, 1920s-1950s (Box 9, Folder 8-15)
  - Magazines, 1933-1937 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Magazines, 1944-1948 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - "Still Life with Red Herring, Harper's Magazine, 1949 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Unidentified Poster, undated (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Clippings of Emily Genauer Columns, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
- Photographs, circa 1930s-1970s; Series 6; 1.8 Linear feet Box 9-12
  Photographs date from circa 1930s to 1970s and include black and white photographs of works of art, as well as portraits of Emily Genauer and her house.
  - Art Jury, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1930s-1950s (Box 9, Folder 21-23)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1930s-1950s (Box 10, Folder 1-19)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1930s-1950s (Box 11, Folder 1-4)
  - Photographs of Emily Genauer, circa 1940s-1970s (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of House, circa 1970s (Box 11, Folder 6)